anna hi how you doing how's your tennis
going are you playing a lot
yeah i started going to delaware clinic
are you going to a clinic
how many times a week twice a week ago
oh that's nice and then you play with
other people too or
yeah it's a bunch of people who are
interested in tennis no but i mean
outside the clinic do you play by
yourself
i go to the wall nice nice
and then you play with me like once a
week yes so this is great you're almost
playing every day
so officially i can't call you a
beginner anymore now you are
intermediate player but you know i saw
you actually posting something on tic
tac of yourself playing on the wall
yes and i noticed on your forehand a
little technical thing that i like to
help you with today
okay okay okay anna so go ahead and hit
a few forehands
i'm going to point out to you
you took your you took your sleeves off
how come why
i don't know people don't like it seems
like
people are very excited people are
obsessed with the sleeves okay
but you the way the way you explained to
me is for sun protection right yes
because you don't want to get like
sunspot florida i want my
of course in my neck i put spf and i
just care of myself
of course you do that's very smart but
the sun is dangerous go ahead and go on
the baseline there
i'm gonna point out the little thing
that i saw on your forehead when i was
watching it on the wall
so the way you're doing your backswing
is not necessarily wrong but there's a
better way and see what you're doing
you're going from the bottom
and then the racket kind of stops right
here and then you go back forward
you're not really generating any
momentum see the racket is going
back and now you have to bring it back
forward as opposed to going
from a higher place and then the racket
naturally falls down and the gravity
helps to create a little bit more
momentum
yeah with gravity does that make sense
you're going up and then the racket kind
of falls
on so look you're going from the bottom
and then you come in here on top and you
bring the racket back down
you're doing extra movements but what's
actually happens to a lot of players
that do
take the racket back from the bottom
without a loop they end up pausing and
waiting here
right the best place to pause on the
forehand is with the racket being to the
side
like this and then when you initiate the
stroke that's when you actually start
the backswing meaning that the racket's
going to go back like this
there you go that's where the stroke
starts and also when you're setting up
the stroke
you have been setting up the stroke by
going down here and then kind of running
like this
and this is not a good way to set up if
you ever watch sprinters they
always have their hands closer together
when they're set up so when you're
setting up the stroke meaning when
you're tracking the ball
your hands are going to be to the side
and then when you're in a good position
and ready to strike
the racquet will start going back so the
first progression i'm going to teach you
is to for you to get comfortable with
bringing the racquet up
before it goes down so go ahead and
place your racket in front of mine
in front of mine like this and hold it
with one hand i'm gonna drop the ball
and now you're gonna go over my racket
and you're gonna hit the ball underneath
my racket okay
so you're building a loop into your
stroke okay i'm going to drop the ball
and you hit it this way do it again
there it is beautiful
again nice shot
okay another one you're building
momentum
from this little looping action can you
feel the difference do it again
very nice and do one more
very nice okay now do it by yourself
nice job very nice
make sure you're going up and then down
up and down
and over the shoulder very nice job
beautiful forehand that was the best one
you hit so far and i'm going to show you
a natural way how to get to this loop
so you don't even have to think about it
so in a ready position you're going to
be switching to your forehand grip
once you see the ball going to your
forehand and i simultaneously you're
also going to be turning towards your
side so the first thing you're going to
do is
turn your grip and also turn your body
to this side
and see how naturally the racket ends up
a little bit higher one thing
that tells me that you're in a forehand
grip go ahead and stand right here
is that the strings are going to be
orientated towards the side so go ahead
and find the forehand grip which is
right here correct and now you're also
going to turn
look what happens here the strings are
orientated to the side yeah and you
get the loop automatically so if you are
in your ready position
have the racket head a little bit higher
when you're waiting for the incoming
ball and as soon as you see your
forehand you're gonna be in your
continental grip right and you're gonna
see it's a forehand you're gonna turn it
here
and you're gonna make a body turn look
the strings are orientated to the side
that's all i want you to think about so
look again ready position
welcome to your forehand turn the grip
and then point the strings
towards the side that's the beginning of
every forehand stroke
once you're in this position now you can
set the forehand up you can move
you know forward or backward or to each
side in this position now the hands are
going to be closer together it's going
to feel a lot more comfortable
and when you initiate the stroke from
there you automatically have
the looping action okay anna so let's
work
on this natural way of creating the loop
so i'm going to feed your ball to your
forehand you're going to
change your grip and then you're going
to turn the strings towards the side
okay see there that was more of a normal
take back so there was more of a normal
take back
you went like this with no loop nothing
okay so go ahead and go in your ready
position again
turn your forehand grip and then turn
the body to there and you're gonna wait
to initiate your stroke from there and
the stroke is initiation starts when the
racket starts going back that's how you
initiate the stroke
this is very important because if you
look at the what's called a modern
forehand
all modern forehands have this loop in
common
it's very important because of several
other factors
now the first move you can make very
quick so you have time
so if you do it slowly you run out of
time so that first move you can do you
can do fast
see fast yeah and so you're waiting here
okay in other words in context of the
incoming ball
as soon as you see the ball going to
your forehand in the ready position you
go
like this and now you set up so that
first part can be very explosive very
fast
so let me cut the stroke a little bit in
half and we're going to wait
we're going to wait here like this so
put your racket here you can have the
hand separated but put the left hand
right next to it
right next to the racket and just wait
like this and hit it from there
do it again
okay anna so you're doing a really good
job waiting for the ball on the side but
you have a little bit of a hard time
with the rotation
so you're not sequencing the rotation
properly see what happens on
this modern forehand is that the left
arm your non-dominant arm is going to be
across the body like this okay because
you're holding the racket and then when
you let go the racket goes back and what
this left hand needs to do it needs to
start the chain in motion so the left
arm needs to get out of the way
so you can start rotating the body and
because what needs to happen is the
contact needs to occur with the dominant
shoulder in front so again watch what
you don't want to do is wait here too
long and then swing like this you're
going to make contact too far behind
that's what's happening now
so the left arm needs to get out of the
way and start this whole process which
is going to initiate the torso rotation
and i'm going to show you a really easy
way how to practice this
sequencing of the torso rotation okay so
which part of the body
leads the whole torso rotation and it's
your left arm so all you're going to do
is you're going to stretch your
non-dominant arm across the body you're
going to hold the ball
and now you're going to have the racket
to the side like you did before
and i'll simply drop the ball and then
hit a forehand see naturally what
happens
if you do that let me show you towards
the camera you can stand on this side
if i don't get my left arm out of the
way in other words if i drop the ball
and i keep my left arm here i'm going to
whack myself in the hand
so naturally as i drop the ball the left
arm
gets out of the way watch because i need
to create the space in front of me so my
racket can comfortably swing
around the body and this is the perfect
timing for this
torso rotation to be initiated by the
non-dominant arm
so go ahead and try it out staying right
here on the baseline and i'll stretch
the number across the body holding the
ball the strings are going to be
pointing towards the side
let the ball go and then get the left
arm out of the way
okay when you do that you need to swing
the arm out of the way
and do what i call the handshake tuck
because this arm can't be like floating
around in the air like that
you need to start here look and you're
going to come around you're going to
tuck it in
imagine shaking somebody's hand and at
the same time you tuck in watch again
here
and then you just you just tuck it in
now while it's pulling away the torso is
rotating you see this
robot yeah remember that and i'll tuck
it in
pull it no no it's not rotating you're
waiting you go you're going like this
and now you're waiting
watch me you see this
you're doing like here and then you're
waiting waiting and then going
so you're hitting the ball behind
you see it so here i mean you're feeding
yourself
yeah but the leading motion for the heat
is coming from from the left side
from the body the body and then it takes
place as a
tutor train absolutely absolutely 100
percent
the body leads the body leads the arm
and in specific it's the left side of
the body that leads
the rotation that's the first link in
the chain yeah but you have to be very
careful not to do this
too early because the sequencing of it
is very subtle
in other words you can easily start
going too early here and now you're
you're opening yourself up too much and
too early
so it's a very subtle timing where the
practice with the ball is excellent for
that because once you
drop the ball then racket goes back and
you start pulling it away
so you have to suddenly start moving
early with that left side
exactly tuck
better tuck it in keep going though
you're waiting
look you're going here and then you're
waiting and then going it's
once you start the rotation doesn't stop
anymore you let it go
yep and what's going to happen the
racket's going to come afterwards it's
going to lag
behind okay but just keep it going the
racket will follow
okay much better that was the best one
you hit so far
much better very nice did i feel
different
from the forehand before so you're using
the whole body now yeah all right so
let's try it without
dropping the ball i'm going to feed it
to you
how i feel it's like
like that yes that's what it feels like
yeah so this
goes as a momentum of the body it does
it does but one thing is that go ahead
like i'm just like saying like
roughly the idea of the movement
that's how you interpret it like that
okay this is actually very good thing
you you bring up
the one thing i don't like about it is
that when you do this movement you see
how loose the arms are
right it's too loose you're not gonna be
able to put enough control
on the ball if the arm is too loose it's
gonna be too sloppy the racquet head is
not gonna be stable enough
so you do need to hold the racket with a
little bit of firmness now obviously not
too tight but not too loose either this
is usually going to result in a lot of
mistakes
but generally the idea of that is
correct but i do want you to
to hold the racquet with some stability
and some firmness okay okay
so we're going to start here right start
here the same process as before you're
going to be in a forehand grip
and now just pretend like you're tossing
the ball to yourself and pulling that
left arm out of the way
remember strings to the side it's very
important to wait here
now it doesn't have to be far away it
can be also bent oh yeah whatever is
comfortable yeah as long as the strings
are towards the side
nice good
all right very good so the next
progression let me actually rally with
you a little bit we hit back and forth
and you try to do the same technique
do it again okay see now the thing
you're not doing is you're not turning
fast you're like waiting like this
okay so you got to make a fast turn
remember ball comes to the forehand go
here
okay remember don't wait here
if you wait for the ball here now the
whole stroke is going to be too fast
so if you wait for the ball here then
you're turning and swinging at the same
time it's going to feel rushed it's
going to feel hectic so the first thing
you do
is you're going to turn like this
much better maybe the best one you hit
so far good job
nice
nice anna
nice good let's try to rally come on
back to me
good again
so what happens is when i start rallying
with you and the ball starts coming
quicker
everything goes out the window you know
you start to rush and all of a sudden
you know what the racket looks like
it's going like this you know it's
swinging like crazy there's no more
technique there's nothing you start to
panic a little bit so
take your time you got plenty of time
believe it or not you don't have to rush
yeah see with most players panic sets in
once the ball comes back a little
quicker so they first thing they do is
they start taking a racket back
very quickly the first thing they do is
think about how they're going to hit the
ball
back and they forget to turn the body
they forget to set up the ball
all right thinking too much don't think
too much i just want everything
would be perfect you have a you have a
really good forehand the one thing i
want you to focus on
is as soon as the ball is coming to your
forehead side i want you to turn
and have the strings towards the side
this is what we're learning today we're
learning a loop
and the loop is going to happen
naturally if you make this first move
correctly
yes all right let's do it again
good again good
better that was a good rally nice
good good
excellent anna wow
wow so
good it's amazing that's the modern
forehand
anna do you understand now the concept
oh it's so exciting
yeah the whole feeling you can feel it
right the whole body feel it the whole
body's working where before
the arm was working a little bit over
time it was just the arm was working by
itself
now you're using the whole body to help
the arm out so when you hit the ball
really hard
this way it's going to feel like you're
not putting any effort into the stroke
yeah
i have a glimpse of the heel how it
should feel
that's great so i want to practice
awesome awareness and body
consciousness you know awesome all right
great job let's do a racket tape
awesome